Okay. Uh we'll get started. Um this is the second of the post training
lectures and we're going to talk about well we're going to finish off the
lecture from from Tuesday first. Uh whatever remaining content we have. Um and then we'll talk about reinforcement
learning from verifiable rewards kind of the new exciting thing that's been happening over maybe the last six months
or so. um and really powering all of these reasoning models that you kind of
see uh dominating the landscape. So, uh, before I get into the verifiable rewards
part, um, the exciting, you know, math RL content, um, I'm going to go back and
I'm going to finish off RLHF, right? So, this is, uh, a very very quick recap of
the last few slides from Tuesday's lecture, right? So, we want to do reinforcement learning from human
feedback, which is the setting where we observe pair-wise preference data, like which of the two responses are better,
and we'd like to get a language model policy that sort of maximizes some sort
of underlying reward. um for this preference data, right? Um and if you remember, DPO is this algorithm that
allows to allows us to optimize this reinforcement learning objective. And this objective is hard because our
language model, the policy, so to speak, is is on the bottom of this expectation,
right? You're sampling from your language model. You're not just maximizing uh the likelihood under the
language model. Um, and the way we're going to do this, um, you know, if you
remember the derivation is that we're going to, you know, make the nonparametric assumption that our policy
class is the set of all functions. We're going to rewrite the reward as a ratio
of the policies. Um, and then plug that in to the Bradley Terry objective. And
so what we're going to do is we're going to find a policy such that sort of the
implied reward maximizes the probability of seeing sort of the references uh, sorry, the pair-wise preferences that we
see, right? Um so now this is great because it's basically supervised learning on a kind of alternatively
parameterized objective. Um which is nice. Um DPO updates have this following
form. Um the reason why you know DPO has kind of took the world by storm for a
bit um a year ago or so um is that it can be written in this very nice form
where you know what you're going to do is you're going to take these gradient
steps which are going to be you know multiplied by beta. That's kind of your
regularization. You're going to have higher weight when your reward estimates are wrong. So
you're going to update more when your sort of implied rewards are are not
correct. Um and then it you're going to increase the likelihood of the good
example and you're going to decrease the likelihood of the bad example. Right? As
I was kind of saying, if you sort of remember what I was saying last lecture,
um really RL algorithms kind of boil down often to just upweight the good
stuff, downweight the bad stuff. And the subtlety really is in deciding, you know, h what the good stuff is and how
much to upweight, right? And so this is one particular choice of doing that. And
we'll see, you know, other things happen. Uh and so DPO um works pretty
well. Um for a while essentially all the open model releases use some variant of
a DPO uh to do their post training. Um and really it's just very easy to get
working um compared to to uh PO. And so for a while it was um really the
dominant approach. Um in the the time since then there was a huge flood of
papers that was like you know asterisk PO. Basically everyone wanted to come up
with a DPO variant. There was dozens and dozens of papers. Um there's so many
that I don't think it's it's worth it to go over the big uh ocean of such papers.
Um, I'll mention two, um, not because necessarily that I think they're like the right ones, but because I think
they're ones that have been used recently, um, by people that are sort of
really pushing the limits of of this kind of DPO style post training. One is
SPIO. Um, and SPIO just makes a very simple modification or two simple modifications. Um, the first one is to
really normalize the update size by the length of the responses. Um, we'll see
kind of this theme appearing later. Um, and the other thing they do is they just
get rid of the reference. So now we've lost the DPO sort of mathematical
argument that you know what we're doing is looking at ratios of policies but
well this is more purely looking at something looks like something where we upweight you know the um the good stuff
and downweight the bad stuff under that sort of underlying motivation simpio totally fine um there's other variants
uh where you don't do necessarily this like reference policy removal where you just sort of normalize by length um
called length normalized dpo um that kind of people have done. Um, and this,
you know, these two forms, DPO with length normalization and simpio were the things that were tried, you know, pretty
extensively by, uh, AI2 folks when they did Tulu 3. Um, and I think one thing
that I'll point out, so I'm going to pause for a moment because I feel like
this is an important conceptual, not conceptual, just an important empirical point, which is that in RL a lot of the
the findings are very very contingent on the specific setting, right? So depending on the environment in which
you run it, depending on the base model that you have, depending on the the
post-training preferences that you're running on, you will find pretty different conclusions. Um, and so one
example of this, right? So, uh, you know, a bunch of the AI2 folks have been
doing a lot of really good post-training empirical work. Um, and they had one
work where they were sort of comparing DPO and PO and they had found that PO
was better than DPO um, because of maybe it's on policiness and they show this,
you know, this jump exactly is the DPO to PO gap. Um, and then in a later work
in Tulu 3, they find actually if you do your SFT in a sort of nicer, better way,
actually that just eats up all the gains of both PO and DPO. So neither of these
really get any gains. And the only thing that does better is maybe DPO with
normalization, right? Like pretty different conclusions. Of course, a lot is different between this left and right
paper. Um, but it's not that one is wrong and the other is wrong. really
that you should be careful about reading too many like generalized conclusions about any of this stuff on the basis um
of one paper right so that's an important note even as I go and talk
about you know PO and I go and talk about uh GRPO later in this you
shouldn't really take any single experimental result necessarily as gospel okay so the last thing I want to
end with for RLHF um is sort of two important things um and one of them will
really just motivate I think the entirety of today's lecture so I think that's important so the first is
overoptimization. Um so in some sense this is just overfitting in fancier naming but it is a a term that I think
is very important because what it's saying is essentially as you optimize your policy more and more so think about
this x-axis as how much RLI did initially your reward kind of goes up
and up and up but eventually you know the reward that reward models that you
fitted on human preferences are diverging from you know real human preferences and the more you optimize
you eventually kind of diverge out right like you're not doing any better you're
just you know optimiz optimizing uh but not actually improving your rewards, right? So this overoptimization thing
appears basically everywhere in RHF. It is a very big problem. Um and so that
that is kind of a a concern. Um and overoptimization is a phenomenon that
really happens in many ways because of the noisiness of human preferences and the complexities of human preferences.
So so um some of my students had a study where you know they basically did RLHF
on human preferences. They did RLHF on noisy versions of, you know, AI feedback
and then they did RLHF on non-noisy versions of human feedback. And you see
clear over optimization phenomena both for humans and for noisy AI feedback, but not really for sort of clean
noiseless um AI feedback. And so really, you know, if you're going to be
post-raining, you should expect to see curves that look like things on the left. as you train your model to do
better and better on your sort of proxy rewards that you've measured, you're not
necessarily going to get better and better models in terms of uh sort of
human preference win rates. Okay? And then the other thing which is an important side note is that when you do
RL, right, remember that I said that we're no longer in probabilistic world, right? So when you're doing supervised
fine-tuning or when you're doing pre-training, it's quite clear that what you're doing is you're trying to do
probabilistic modeling on some distribution, right? you're doing distribution matching for something, right? Um, but RLHF is all it's all just
a policy. There's no underlying necessarily distribution. And how this manifests is that often you'll get much
less calibrated models, right? A number of results across many different papers have shown that, you know, RLHF models
um often, especially at temperature one, you know, show much more overconfident behavior. So, this one was from one of
the anthropic papers. This one was from, I think, the GPT4 release. Um this one
was from a a paper that one of my posttos did. In all these cases
essentially the RLHF models are much less calibrated and maybe that's fine right because calibration isn't part of
the reward that you're putting in. So so that's you know as designed but you
should be very careful thinking of these models as sort of calibrated probabilistic models which you might be
sort of tempted to do if you're kind of coming into this from a generative
modeling um background. So, okay. Um, so up until now, we've been kind of
thinking about um, RLHF and all these things. Actually, I'll stop for a moment. If anyone has any final
questions for RLHF, I'll answer them before I go on because we're going to
totally switch topics to uh, RL from verified rewards in a moment. Yes. Uh, going back to the human
preferences graph, what's what are the two axes that that we're looking at? This one? Yeah. Yeah. So, the x-axis is
proxy reward. So, um, here we're fitting like a reward model. We're not we're not
doing VPO here, right? So let's say we're doing something like PO where we
fit a a reward uh classifier and the X-axis is saying how well did my RL
algorithm optimize that reward classifier. Right? So this is success at RL on is on the X- axis. Y-axis is this
is kind of like true win rates either measured by you know AI feedback here or
human feedback. So this is like real human votes you know on the y- axis
here. Um, and so this is saying you might think that succeeding at RL will
make you succeed at the actual task that you know you're trying to optimize for.
That's not the case. It will overfit at some point for at least human
preferences. Um, yes. So question why is it written in that not like beta
log a minus log b or just like log of a b like are you just asking like why
don't they like pull the fractions out in the log or because I thought is this
like a numeric computation thing that like when you take these two ratios the
taking the log is easier to compute and that's why we want to do no I don't
think that I think taking ratios is actually add numerically. So I think this is really just like a save the
space you know the ratios you know are more compact and they're also intuitive objects right so the moment
you put simple it becomes a different form because you no longer have the same
beta concept yes that's right yeah simpio is just like a very different motivation for why you would do this
thing right there's no ratios it's a very fundamentally different object yes in the graph where you showed like a
more sort of hacking thing um I was wondering like how you like how the
measure like you know the ground truth of like the reward score, right? Cuz
presumably the reward function is a model like the human preference, right? But it's kind of like a train test gap,
right? The x-axis here, you know, you have a train set, you fit a reward model
on it and you're measuring that fitted reward model, right? And the y-axis is
fresh samples from the true reward oracle, right? Um and so they're measuring in expectation the same thing,
but they're not measuring in finite sample the same thing. like the same this is the same as like train test gaps
in machine learning right same conceptual object they are in expectation measuring the same thing um
for any finite sample that's not the case okay good um so I think you know
all this questions about um reinforcement learning from human feedback I think brings up a good point
which is that you know human feedback is very difficult to optimize it's very
difficult to scale and so you might wonder are there other kinds of more
effective RL that we can bring to bear on post training right And that's going
to get us here, right? So, up until now, we've been kind of talking about chat
GBD 3.5 and that era of models. And now I think we want to talk about 01 and the
the you know the new set of kind of reasoning style models, right? And the
way we're going to get there is kind of this thinking of saying, okay, we have
this very powerful tool now. We have this reinforcement learning tool that we can use for post- training. Um, and
initially, you know, the the instinct was to say, you know, there's one true
objective, and that objective is whether people like the bot, right? And so, if
we just optimize for the true objective we care about, that's all we need. Turns
out to be very difficult, right? Human uh human uh approval is easy to hack.
It's hard to collect at scale. It's hard to RL at scale. For all those reasons,
you see, you know, overoptimization and all these kind of issues. On the other
hand, we could instead turn to to where RL has really dominated, right? things
like alpha go or alpha fold. And then you know looking at those domains you
might say you know what we really need is kind of a domain which we know the
true reward and for which we can evaluate such true rewards very quickly and efficiently and at scale right and
if we could do that then we can bring to bear all of the successes of
reinforcement learning from the past into language modeling. Right? So that's the overall mindset that we're we're
we're adopting now. Right? We have the tools that we've built. Now let's apply
them into a very kind of different way of using the same tools, right? Taking
inspiration from successes in in RL. Okay. Um and so today I'm going to talk
in two parts, right? So the first part is just going to be an algorithmic part,
right? So this part on the very top I'm going to talk about different um
algorithms. First I'm going to talk about PO in more detail because you know
I kind of cut that from last lecture for length reasons. And then I'm going to
transform PO into GRPO. um a simpler version in some sense and then we'll
talk through those objectives and various uh implementation details of
GRPO um to get us to multiple like canonical variations of GRPO and having
done that we will then walk through the three I think uh big reasoning model
sort of training things that have been done as case studies um since after part
one you'll have all the tools that you need to understand everything that is
happening in part two right and after you do part two you'll understand at
least how these three uh Chinese open LMS were made. Okay, so now we are going to return to
PO. Um it is the thing that I didn't want to do but we have to do in order
for you to understand why GRPO exists, right? Um so what is PO? Um at least in
my sort of mental model of what PO is, we start from the simplest possible
thing and then we move you know slowly but surely downwards to PO, right? So
the simplest possible thing um I mentioned this in last lecture. This is the policy gradient, right? So on the
left, I would like to optimize the expected reward under my policy P of
theta, right? Um, and we're going to optimize that through gradient descent. So I take the gradient of that object
and I get the right hand side of that equation, which is the policy gradient,
the expectation uh under my current policy of the reward and I'm going to
take gradient steps that sort of either increase or decrease the probability according to the sign of the reward Z.
Right? Um, hopefully straightforward. Um if this is not familiar to you, you can
sort of brush up on how that policy gradient derivation happens. Now um there are two things that we might want
to to think about uh here that are kind of inefficient, right? So the first
thing is that this is uh what you might call purely on policy, right? So the way
that the reinforced gradients work, I have to sample from P theta and then I
will immediately take a step uh on those sampled examples, right? And so every
time that I want to take a gradient step, I have to compute a reward, right?
and I have to do a roll out. You will sort of understand this in your in your
assignment five, but the expensive part of RL is the rollouts, right? We have to
actually run the language model and get samples. And we know that that's slow,
right? From Percy's inference lecture, we know that that's very complicated. It's very tricky. Um, we would much
rather sample less frequently, right? We we do a roll out once, we sample once,
and then we take multiple updates on those rollouts. So that motivates something called TRPO, right? where
instead of taking updates from P theta, I would like to allow my sort of updates
to go stale. So what I'm going to do is I'm going to sample from um P theta old,
this sort of base distribution down here um but still get sort of valid policy
gradients. Well, how can I do that? Well, I can do what's called an
important sampling correction and then I can keep, you know, um, my policies close to my old one so that I don't get
too far uh, from my old one and get sort of crazy reward estimates. Right? Very
simple idea. Just do a little bit of off to on policy correction. You get
something called TRPO. This a of T is a lower variance version of R of Z. I'm
not going to talk about advantage estimation uh, in much more detail. PO is a is a simple extra step beyond this.
It says, you know, instead of doing KL divergences, I'm just going to clip the
advantages. And this is naturally going to force my policy to remain close because if I go too far, then I'm not
going to be able to get higher and higher rewards. These rewards will just
get clipped off at sort of a one minus epsilon or one plus epsilon. There's an
upper bound to how much reward I can collect. So there's no incentive for the
RL algorithm to make the policy really different from the current one, right? So it's a soft version you can say think
of kind of this idea. Okay, so PO very successful RL algorithm um used in many
different places um you know used in sort of very toy RL environments uh it
was used in OpenAI sort of Dotaabot um works very well in such actual RL tasks
oh yeah there was a video I forgot about that yeah look you can run around yeah
okay um and at a conceptual level it's not that complicated right um if you go
look at the openai documentation uh for PO it looks fairly simple right you see
that equation that I listed above, it's this po clip objective. And really the
only thing that's maybe slightly complicated is that this a of t is actually calculated by using something
called a value function. So you need a second neural network to essentially compute kind of the expected rewards. Um
and that would be used to to in some sense lower the variance of my
gradients, right? Um I'm not going to go into the details once again of of sort
of all the RL details but you know the one implementation uh difference here
that matters is that we need this value function and that will become important
in a moment here. Um but PO in practice is a very very
different beast from PO in theory. Um and you know you're in for a very bad
time if you know there's a blog post that says 37 implementation details of
PO. Um you know I don't want to know all 37 of those guys. Um, and you know, it's
a there's a huge long list of sort of different PO variants in this blog post
and all of them have the different scores on the RL uh benchmarks and
there's a whole paper written on why implementation details matter in PO and how if you really mess it up, you're not
even computing the policy gradient correctly anymore, but it actually works better, right? Um, so it's kind of a a
crazy place. Um, if you look at the implementation details of PO and so we
actually do have to maybe look at a live implementation detail. Um, I'll actually
go over it quickly because PO isn't the point of this lecture. But what I want
to get across to you is, you know, you all haven't been necessarily working on
this post- training space. Like why do people care so much about alternatives to PO? It is because of things like
this, right? PO works well, but it is kind of a beast. Um, and this is one
example I think from the early days of RLHF uh re-implementations. Um, there was this nice diagram
describing, you know, this is how you would do a pretty standard implementation of PO. This diagram is
pretty gnarly, right? We've got a reward model for RLHF. We've got a value model
that's supposed to keep track of kind of the expected reward. Um, we've got
generalized advantage estimation. I haven't even explained what that is. Um, and that's going to go into the policy
um, language model. and we're going to do, you know, our policy gradient updates. So there's there's all this
sort of machinery that has to go into place for PO to work. Um so we're going
to look at an implementation. Um a few years back now actually um some of my
students and I did you know reimplementations of algorithms like PO um and other people have used it. So
this is an implementation that's been somewhat tested. Not to say that this is
a good implementation. I'm sure you know something like uh more modern implementations from Volcano Engine and
other things uh probably work a little bit better but I just want to walk you
through all the different components. Um also because as you write um GRPO in
your assignments your structure will probably mirror some aspects of this right all RL algorithms have similar
kind of outer loop. So um if we look at this right so a a PO step looks very
similar to a standard uh gradient update step uh in a language model. So this is
the outer sort of loop. What we're going to do is we're going to you know get a
bunch of rollouts. Um and once we get you know a bunch of rollouts what we're
going to do is we're going to compute some losses and then we're going to just
take backwards and then gradient steps with you know clip norm and that's it
right very unintimidating. the outer loop of of RL is is usually fine, right?
Um, you know, loss computation is also basically the same thing. So, um, this
is probably uh small for those of you in the back. Um, but if you look at this,
you know, what you have is one block that's computing the loss for the value
function. Remember, PO has both a value function and a policy. So, we have to
update both of those at once. So, we're computing how close is the value
function to kind of the actual sort of returns, the rewards that we saw. Um,
and we want to keep those close because the value function is supposed to
provide variance reduction. And then we've got the actual sort of rewards that we're going to update on for uh PO.
And then we have sort of the clipping constants 1 - epsilon 1 plus epsilon.
This code is literally just copying this back over. And just to give you sort of
some, you know, intuition for hyperparameters, you know, a typical clip range might be something like 02
here, right? So, so you would be allowed to go essentially from 0.8 to 1.2 two in
likelihood ratio between your old and new policy. Um the rollouts is where
things start to get gnarly, but this is still essentially just calling inference. The left side is really just
sampling, you know, rollouts from your current policy and then you evaluate the log problems of your samples and you
move on to the right and what do you see? Well, uh the only subtlety here is
that your value and your reward and your policy may have different tokenizers. So
you got to do retokenization. But otherwise you just feed your rollouts into the model. So okay, at this point
you're like looking at this code and you say okay that's fine like this is not
not so horrible. Um but the places where things start to get a little bit tricky.
Um is first we have to do some reward shaping right? So what does this mean?
Um so stepping slightly back. One thing that's weird about reinforcement learning for language models is if you
you know think about it from the RL perspective technically it's kind of like a contextual bandit. Well, what
what is a contextual bandit? A contextual bandit is something where you get an input and you have a bunch of
possible, you know, uh actions to take and you immediately get a reward, right?
In language modeling, you get a prompt, you can give an output, and you
immediately get a reward. There's no like state transitions. There's no environment exploration. There's none of
this like complexity, right? Um reward shaping here is essentially constructing
um uh per token losses in order to be able to give you something more uh easy
to learn for the RL algorithm. And so what happens in practice for PO and for
GRPO which you'll be implementing um is that the KL terms essentially the regularization that we're applying is
actually computed per token whereas the um actual true reward like the did you
complete the task or not kind of thing that's computed at the very last token.
Right? So you see that there's essentially a per token reward for the regularization and there's a single
terminal reward at the end for um success or not. Yes. What does it mean?
What does not work? Um, oh, right, right, right. This is um this is a Right, right. This is uh kind
of funny. This basically we're only adding per token KL penalty, but once again, this is one of those funny um uh
PL implementation things. Um this second line here, this is the actual true KL
calculation. Um but when this number goes to negative, um it becomes numerically unstable and you can
actually hit that pretty often. And so this gets clamped off at zero, which you
know all of you know if you clip off a a log likelihood uh ratio at zero that's
not a KL anymore, but it is some approximation to a KL. Yes. What are um
so we've talked about like boss function. What are our update steps
especially like as it relates to the um the reward function? Is that the same as
other Yeah. Yeah. Good good point. So the the updates you know as I was saying
in this outer loop is actually just taking gradient steps. So in terms of
your code it will look no different than just taking you know normal gradient
steps. Um what is happening here though is in some sense uh let's go back to the
policy gradient equation here. Um right if you write down this thing this is r
of z * p theta z. This is kind of like just taking gradients with respect to
theta of rzp log p theta z. It's a weighted loss that you then take
gradients of. Um, and what you're not doing is technically if you're taking a
real gradient, you should also take a gradient into P theta, but you don't do
that. There's kind of a stop implicit stop gradient. And so all you do is you
compute this inner loss, you feed it to the autograd, and you'll get the right
steps for the rein uh for the policy gradient. Um, yeah, you'll have to do that for for
the assignment as well. And we have like a little tutorial that explains kind of
what's going on there in case that that quick explanation was not clear. Okay.
And finally, the part that I think is the gnarliest is there's a the box that
I did not explain called generalized advantage estimation, right? Um so what you need to do whenever you have a
policy gradient, um the variances of the gradient are often very high, right? And
so you want to do as much variance reduction as you can. And instead of
multiplying the gradients with uh the rewards directly, you can instead you can show that the following um a of t
quantity which is essentially a discounted um advantage estimate. That's a sort of RL term um is an appropriate
substitute. And so one of the things that PO does that's very different is to
use this advantage estimate where you can tweak lambda um and gamma to trade
off bias and variance uh of your gradients. One of the funny things though is despite kind of the annoyance
of this this implementation complexity of like maintaining this value function and estimating all these quantities um
you can just pick gamma equals lambda equals 1 which reduces this whole thing
basically to a baselined policy gradient. So your guts taking R uh minus the the implied value. Um and that works
well too. And so the point of making you go through this was um a lot of the
implementations details for PO are both simple in that it is just the outer loop
RL. You do just take gradients and also kind of annoying, right? You have to do
all these sort of clipping things. You have to think about what am I going to
do with the generalized advantage estimate. Um what am I going to do to
train the value um estimate? Um but you expect to see, you know, overall
increasing rewards. um including reward models and sort of negative KL rewards kind of go down. This is a once again um
a contextual bandit. So you expect to see pretty reasonable training curves, not like crazy RL ones. Okay, so I went
through PO. Um that was kind of a whirlwind tour, but I think hopefully
you get the context of a what PO is and b that it is sometimes a little bit
tricky to get working right. And so, you know, this has motivated a lot of people
to try to find alternatives to PO. Um, what we're going to want to do is to
apply, you know, essentially these RL algorithms to settings where PO applies. And PO applies very well to to general
RL settings where you have sort of rewards. Um, but we don't want the
complicated implementation. And maybe more importantly, we want to get rid of the value model. That is actually if you
try to implement PO really, really annoying, right? because a value model is usually as big as your policy. So now
in terms of GPU memory, you're paying twice the cost of your language model.
Right? Now you might say, okay, uh why can't we use DPO? Well, DPO is well
suited for like pair-wise comparisons like Bradley Terry comparisons. Um it's not so good if what you want to do is
let's say do reinforcement learning on math questions and check whether or not the answers are correct, right? There's
no pair-wise structure so to speak inherently there. So maybe DPO is not great, right? Um, DPO also, you know,
originally is is kind of an offline algorithm in a sense in that it has a
whole bunch of sort of pairs that you initially collect and you just update
your model on those. You could make it online by iterating, but that's not
usually the way in which uh people apply GPO. So then now this brings us to the new
hotness which I think is uh GRPO, right? So GRPO is actually very very simple um
both in motivation and in actual implementation. So where you start with is conceptually you start at PO, right?
You start with very similar pieces. Um you think about kind of this clipping
thing. You think about policy updates in very similar ways. Um but what you do is
you remove the really complicated generalized advantage estimation. You just get rid of it completely. Um and
you replace it with something that is much much simpler. Right? Uh so what is
the much simpler thing? Well, we are going to replace um the advantage which
used to be this like GA thing. It was the sum o over returns and had the value
function in there. Instead, it's going to be this equation three at the bottom
of this slide here. Um and what is this? Uh the advantage of you know response I
is equal to the reward that response I receives minus the mean of the responses
within my group. And I'll define what a group is in a moment. and then divided
by the standard deviation of the rewards within the group. So this is a zcore uh
if you know what that is um of the rewards within the group. Right? Now
what is a group? A group is a very in some sense natural object for for
language model RL. You have an input question. Let's say like solve this math
problem. Right? That is a group. And I have many different candidate responses. I have capital G uh different responses.
Um and those are all the responses within my single group. Right? So um the
nice thing is if you think about it right maybe problems are harder or
easier right you know some math problems are much harder than others um and
because of that the average reward that my sort of other samples receive is a
natural baseline for myself and and people have explored exactly these kinds of algorithms um if you look up like uh
reinforcement learning with leave one out or sorry policy gradients with leave one out this is the leave one out
baseline um in action minus the standard deviation piece um right
Um the yes I was wondering talking about here like so you said it's
a it's like they have a batch of questions right and then there are
answers to it which are reported so like is each like answer only corresponding
to one unique question or are we doing like multiple like kind of um like
trajectories of the same question for multiple questions right you do multiple answers per question and that's how you
get kind of variance reduction in like multiple different questions and also like kind of like multiple answers
for each of the questions. Is that a really important example? No. No. So for
each question Q, GRPO samples a group of outputs, right? So so I mean this is not
batched like you you normally you would if you were doing this for real, you
would have multiple questions and for each question you'd have G responses and those would get baseline together.
Across questions you would have no baselining or any interaction really other than the policies get updated
together. Okay. So the the baseline is only doing within the same question. And
that that's why the baseline makes sense, right? Because a question is like hard or easy and the mean of that that
reward isn't sometimes capturing the question difficulty and you're subtracting that guy out. Okay, good. Um and the other thing, this
is a fun note. Um I I'm going to mention it because I just kind of think this is
fun and cool. Uh this DKL, uh if you've seen lots of KL divergence computations,
um this is actually a little non-standard, right? uh because the natural kale divergence estimate is
actually just you you take a bunch of samples and then you compute the average
of the log ratio which is kind of this inner term over here right um but this
one from from gpo actually has these two extra terms it has the log or has the
ratio of pi ref over pi theta and has this minus one um and you can kind of
convince yourself that if you take the expectation of this with respect to pi
theta um you know this is just going to be uh cancelling with this one over
here. So this is a control variant scheme that reduces the variance of uh
this KL divergence estimate which is cool uh because maybe you all need to
estimate KL divergence from samples. Uh this equation two is just a slightly nicer way of estimating that exact same
thing. Okay. Um and GRPO is really nice. Um oh one last note. Um if you're only taking
one step which is doing the pure online case, right? all this clipping stuff
just kind of disappears and all you're doing is policy gradients, right? Policy gradient is just upweing good stuff and
downweing bad stuff where the rewards that I'm multiplying the policy gradients by is this avi. So it's just
like an incredibly simple algorithm for the the truly online case where you're not doing multiple steps on a single
example. Um so there's multiple kind of different repositories um for gpo implementations. Um I I can point you to
several including uh this one that I sort of copied and put onto this slide
here. Um but basically uh I can just say that it's it's exactly the way you think
it would go. Um sort of in the outer loop you would compute the reward for
each nor roll out you normalize for each group the the mean and the variance of
the rewards. You'd compute the KL term in this case per sequence which isn't
quite right uh for the more heavyweight implementations. And then you do gradient updates on the loss. And this
is you know one example of the loss computation that you also have here. Um
and the advantage computation unlike in the uh PO case is just really really
simple. Uh this is almost exactly you know line for line the equations that I
showed you with just one minor difference that's not shown in the equation which is that you know as you
do in almost everything because we're dividing by the standard deviation you add a tiny fudge factor of 1 eg4 to to
make sure it doesn't numerically uh blow up on you right and you'll have to do
this in the assignment as well. you'll have to add a little epsilon uh to your
gpo uh setup. So, how well does this work? Um gpo works pretty well. Um this is from the
original uh deepseek math paper. Um and I'll get back to this later because it
is interesting um to look at this this plot and this result in light of later
R1 results. Um they show essentially uh the two fine-tuning based methods uh RF
and online RFT. This is basically a a fairly weak baseline I would say. um
where what you're doing is you're only looking at examples that sort of get the
right answer. They're doing math in this case. So you only get examples where you
get the right answer and you fine-tune on your own outputs that got the right
answer. Right? Reinforcing uh correct answers with fine-tuning. Um GRPO with outcome level rewards where you only get
a correct or not answer is the yellow. The blue one is process level rewards
where it's kind of you got a system that looks at each step of your reasoning and
sort of gives you a grade for that. And they're arguing, you know, maybe process
rewards are better. We'll talk a little bit more about that later. But in in
either case, you see that gpo works and it works um pretty well. Okay, any questions about the basic gpo
piece before we move on to kind of details about gpo and thinking kind of
deeply about what's actually happening in the algorithm?
Good. Okay. So now let's think about uh the difference between uh gpo and po and
and what we've done and what's different. Okay. So really there's, you know, as I was saying, only one
difference, although it's a really important difference. It's replacing the advantage estimator with this thing,
right? The the mean uh or the zcore, let's say, of the rewards. Um, and so
now I'm going to kind of go back to uh the policy gradient theorem or the
policy gradient result, and I'm going to think through this result with you, right? So when we uh when we take a
policy gradient update, right, what can we do? So I'll just go back a couple
slides, right? Um on this slide, we've got right here at the very top policy gradients. This is
the most basic RL algorithm that you can do, right? You take gradients where you
multiply the log probability gradients with the reward. Right? This is something that I'm always allowed to do.
This is a mathematical equivalence. Right? Now, one other thing I can do is
called baselining. I can take this reward Z and I can subtract any constant
uh or any in fact any random variable that doesn't depend on uh Z itself. Um
and this would still be a valid uh policy gradient. Right? So so this
baselining thing is really important because what you're going to try to do is you're going to try to subtract
constants that give you lower variances on this expectation. Right? So that's called baselining. Um and if we go here,
you know, that's kind of um a classic result that you can look up in Senarto.
They say, okay, look, we've got the policy gradient. You can subtract out any baseline B of S because B of S, you
know, when we sum it up across the policy is going to be zero, right? Um so
this is fine, right? We can always baseline, but let's look at this A of A
of I. Is this a baseline? Well, um, we're subtracting the mean and that's
kind of a baseline because all the other rewards are not dependent on RO of I. So
maybe that's okay. I mean, technically this notation includes RO of II, but if
I remove that, that's a valid baseline. But one thing that's really weird is I'm
dividing by the standard deviation here, right? That that's not something that really seems allowed according to this
derivation in Senardau. Um, and that turns out to be a problem. uh some folks uh that have gone and you
know reanalyzed gpo and its behaviors basically argue that gpo has two things that at least mathematically are a
little bit off. Um and the first thing is this division by standard deviation
right as I was kind of talking you through just now this breaks that sort
of you know contract that a baseline just needs to be subtracting a zero mean
uh variable uh that's you know independent of of my draw. Um, and the
other thing that GRPO does, uh, which I did it kind of, sorry, I glossed over
when I previously presented it, is that it's actually dividing, um, kind of the
rewards by the length of the output. Um, and that's going to have that's also a
little bit weird according to the policy gradient theorem. This is not something that would naturally show up. Um, and so
these authors who did like this this pretty interesting study of uh GRPO algorithms kind of argue that maybe we
should just get rid of these two things. And if you do, then you'll actually have
much shorter output length and higher reward without having much longer responses.
Um, and so let's talk about these results uh, you know, uh, carefully for
each one of these two fixes. Um and hopefully by talking through these you
will gain an intuition about how the RL algorithm works. Right? So first I want
to talk about uh the standard deviation. Um this one's maybe somewhat obvious what it's doing. Um okay let me let me
go back because I think it's easier to talk about when I'm highlighting the
equation here. Um so I'm dividing the advantage by the standard deviation. So what does that mean? When the standard
deviation is small, right, the reward is going to be amplified. it's going to be
more important for me to optimize that group when the standard deviations are small, right? And when is the standard
deviation small? Well, it's when the problem is too easy or it's too hard,
right? Because that's when the rewards are either all zero or they're all ones.
And so there's a bias in the standard deviation term that upweights problems that are too easy or too hard. Um the
authors argue this slows convergence. Maybe true. At the very least, it certainly breaks the validity of the
policy gradient. The second thing which is subtle but also interesting is the length normalization.
Now let's kind of look at what's happening here. So we have this length
normalization before the gpo reward. Now what does that do? If my model got a
question wrong, right? Then the best thing to do is I'm receiving negative reward in here. So the best thing to do
is to make the response really really long. And if I get the answer right, the
best thing to do is to make the answer short so I can sort of maximize my
positive reward. Right? So what this does is it actually produces uh a model
that kind of BS as aggressively as possible. If the model thinks it can't
get the answer right, it just produces the longest possible response, which is a very very bad incentive for you to
give the model. Um and so if you fix this, uh what happens is, you know, on
various sort of toy tasks like GSMAK and so on, you you can get um a reward
that's just as good. The red one is sort of the modified version, but the output
length doesn't keep growing and growing and growing. It sort of like stabilizes at a certain point, right? Um and so
there is actually some interesting observation that like maybe some of the really long coots that people are seeing
in uh things like gRPO are a result of these like actual implementation details
and choices rather than inherently long coots being a necessary part of the performance of these models. And I think
that's like a very interesting although not fully proven out uh class of hypothesis.
Cool. Okay. So that's the GRPO algorithm. Hopefully now you're all familiar with it and I think you now
have the background to go through uh all three of these papers now. Uh deep sea
car 1, Kimmy 1.5 and uh Quent 3. Um any questions? Yes. So a question about why like
operating is bad just to confirm like my understanding. I guess it's bad because
like in those in either the very easy or the very hard cases we don't want to
actually like aggressively update the model. Yeah. I think this gets into sort
of um uh wishy-washy folk theorem territory, but actually some of these papers will talk about this folk theory
and so I'll mention it which is what you really want the RL algorithm to do is to
get problems that it can like do somewhat well on like it can get some
reward on but is not so easy that it can like already solve them right so there's
like kind of a curriculum effect where you want to feed the models the right
you know level of difficulty and if you're maximizing the that standard deviation that's kind of the wrong
direction Right? You're really maxing out the stuff at the extremes that you either already all know or are just way
too hard for you to solve. Um, cool. Okay. So, we're going to talk
about uh all three of these papers today. R1, uh, Kimmy K1.5, and Quen 3.
Um, R1 and K1.5, I think, are pretty interesting because they came out at
roughly the same time. Um, sadly, R1 was the only one to to get like a gigantic
social uh, what's it called? Uh, reception. Um but both of these actually
um show how to do RL based reasoning on like math and other things with LLMs,
right? And they because they're contemporaneous um you can kind of see almost two parallel ways to tackle the
same problem like which things are similar, which things are different and so on which is great. Um Quinn 3 is the
newest of the releases. Um and they do some fairly interesting variations of ideas in R1. Um, and also they have some
new kind of tricks that that R1 doesn't have, which I think are pretty
interesting things to look at, especially if you're interested in things like inference efficiency, uh, of
reasoning models. So, uh, I'll start with R1. Um, I think R1 is, you know, kind of amazing in the
sense that it's a it's a, you know, archive paper that launched a whole
social phenomenon. Never let your advisers tell you that, you know, your archive papers will never matter. you
know, this one uh lost like what almost half a billion dollars of of Nvidia
valuation. You two can one day maybe cause that kind of a wave. Um R1, I
think, is quite remarkable because you know it in many ways replicates all of
the qualitative properties of the 01 recipe in a way that is extremely simple. Um so you know the the key
properties that I want to talk through and and you know make sure you all
understand. Um the first thing right is that you know it hits the performance
targets that open AIO1 set. Everyone was really excited about reasoning model. So this is very exciting. The second thing
is that you know it opens up a RL recipe that is not only just like a replicable
one but I think more importantly one that is extremely simple right it doesn't have any search it doesn't have
any process reward models. I think lots of people at the time thought maybe we
need all these complicated pieces to get reasoning models. R1 really shows you don't need any of that, right? And then
finally, um there's lots of interesting insights about the interaction between supervised fine-tuning um and RL that I
think um continue to be really important. Okay, so uh the starting
point of R1 is they build on deepseek math. Um, and actually some of the
equations I showed you of GRPO are from Deepseek math where they originally proposed GRPO as an alternative simpler
or system more systems efficient variant of PO, right? To them actually the most
important piece was they wanted to get rid of the value model just because it's
really annoying to have around. Um, but one thing that's really interesting is you know they actually go for this
yellow line the outcome supervision which is not actually the best performing model um in deepseek math.
talk about that again at the very end of this this section here. So I'll walk
through all the different pieces of R1. Um so I'll start with R10 uh which I
think of as the controlled setting, right? So R10 um is a very pure form of
RL learning. um it basically takes uh essentially the model that is pre-trained plus mid-trained um before
doing any RLHF or instruction tuning and then throws it into the uh math RL loop
and then they try to find out how well does that do right so the details here
um how do they do the reinforcement learning well they have a bunch of uh
sort of mathish tasks the data is not public um they take deepseeek v3 as
their kind of base model um and then their rewards there's two forms of
rewards that they use. One of them is an accuracy reward. So like did it get the
math question correct? Right? It's a correct or not reward. It's binary. Uh they have a format reward that basically
forces the model to put its coot within like thinking tags like thinking start
thinking end of thinking tags, right? And that's important if you want your model to have these like long coots uh
being used. Now, um the format reward feels like something that doesn't matter, but from many papers and from
having talked to many people, apparently it is a pretty critical part of actually
getting this whole like reasoning RL thing to work. Um once you do this
right, all they're doing is is doing RL on top of the base model. Nothing very
fancy, but the results are are pretty striking. they get performance that is getting pretty close to open AIO1 by
just doing some RL um on top of of the model that they already had, right? Um
without any like, you know, coot fine-tuning or anything like this. Um and there's kind of two things uh that
they note in their paper as being really interesting about R10. Um and I want to
talk about this because I think it's important to to carefully examine what is happening in R10. So the first thing
they say is, "Oh, it's very cool that if you just let the model do RL on this
this verifiable rewards, the length of the coot just kind of increases like pretty predictably." Um, and you know,
in commentary that I don't know if I necessarily agree with, you know, in the
paper they're like, "Oh, it's learning to solve harder and harder problems by thinking harder and harder." It's like,
well, maybe. Um, they also, you know, point out it's kind of cool that, you
know, they learn, you know, phenomena like backtracking. They call this the aha moment. I think much has been made
uh about this in sort of public discourse that wow it's cool that RL
training can give models these kind of emergent insights. Um I'll kind of refer
you back to the the doctor gpo paper the one that was talking about the
corrections to GRPO. Um and I think they have honestly pretty good and interesting arguments that both of these
are not particularly interesting phenomena. Like first of all they argue that like the length just goes up
because of the biased objective not because you know it's an inherently interesting object. Um and second they
they argue well if you just run deepseeek v3 on a bunch of math
questions it'll also sometimes output things like aha I can do this or that
which is maybe not like a deeply new phenomenon that arises from RL. Um you
know both of these seem like given more recent evidence kind of credible uh
things that like maybe there's nothing like emergent and special about R10 but it is actually working very well right
that is a good math model. So R10 you can think of as kind of a
research setting, right? They're taking a controlled model, they're doing something very controlled on top of it,
which is math RL, and they get a good model out, right? But if you're trying
to build a really strong model that you're going to ship to the world, um
this is not what you're going to do, right? You're going to like basically do
everything that you can to get the best model that you can, right? So what would
you do uh in that sort of more unrestricted setting? Well, um you're going to maybe insert some supervised
fine-tuning. you're going to take, you know, coots from, you know, some undisclosed source and you're going to
fine-tune your deepseeek model on that before you do your RL. And after you do
that, right, you don't want your model to be kind of like this math savant that
can't do anything else. So, you're going to, you know, apply your usual post-training pipeline on top of that to
make sure that it can do all the other tasks that, you know, people normally
want to use these models for, right? So, this is kind of the the the pipeline
differences. Um, and so the key differences both within the pipeline and uh within the RL is they do SFT
initialization to try to get the model to to know how to do long coots without
starting with RL. They add a language consistency reward in order to make sure that the chains of thought
remain in a single language and then they do you know a secondary RLHF stage
um kind of at the end. So I think this makes a lot of sense, right? Every time
you want to do something advanced like reinforcement learning, um you're probably going to start by doing a
little bit of supervised fine-tuning. Um and so even in sort of reasoning models
or long coot models like deepcar1, this is the case, right? You start with uh
long coot supervised fine-tuning data and then you're going to, you know, do RL. Um I will point out that the uh
description of where they get this data and what this data is remains very very
vague. like they don't tell us like what was the coot data derived from um how
did they filter it I don't really have any idea based on reading the R1 paper
um the claimed benefit of this is that if you coot the model on sorry if you
sft the model on long let's say English coots then this gives you an
interpretability benefit right as you do RL you're not going to get like weird
gibberish it's going to kind of keep the model closer to these like more
interpretable coots that you started out with um So and and that would be kind of
good for users, right? Like as you're, you know, using a math model, it would
be nice to see its reasoning uh as it goes. Um and an additional thing, right?
So so when they do SFT initialization, they use a ton of data. But one really
interesting thing is that for a lot of models, even a tiny amount of uh SFT on
these kinds of like long coot data can be good. Um, one thing that some of my
students in collaboration with Percy, uh, we did was, um, basically take a bunch of long coots from Gemini 2.0
flash thinking and, you know, fine-tune Quen 2.5. And maybe surprisingly, you know, with just a thousand examples, you
know, you get really, really high, you know, uh, math benchmark accuracy, um, with just a little bit of long coot
fine-tuning. So I think both of these are really pointing to the fact that the
base model already has a lot of kind of like thinking capabilities that you're
just like kind of priming and extracting um from the model. Um and after that of
course you're going to do um RL, right? So after you've gotten the the model set
up with SFT, you know, as with kind of the instruction tuning and RHF pipeline,
so you start with SFT and then you do RL to to basically get the model to to
actually optimize the rewards you're looking for. Um, the RL part is basically the same as R10. Not not huge
differences, but with a a minor difference that you're going to add a language consistency loss. And they have
I think I think this note is is pretty interesting. This is a minor note, but
I'll describe it anyway where they basically say um, you know, they add this like language consistency reward
because, you know, during the training process, if they just let the model RL,
they find that actually the coot will language mix like it will switch between languages. Um, and if many of
you have kind of seen people playing with um, reasoning models, um, I've seen
people on the internet post things like, oh, it's kind of weird that like Grock 3
like suddenly switches to Chinese and the coot. And this is kind of consistent
with those kinds of things that if you aggressively RL a model, like actually,
you know, there's natural tendencies for models to language mix um, rather than staying in a single language. So it
actually requires an additional reward to keep it in the single language.
Um and then finally after you've done RL on like math and other verifiable
domains you basically layer on the usual post training. So you do uh instruction
tuning and then you do sort of the the pair wise preference tuning um
afterwards right so uh they do an SFT spe where they combine both reasoning
data um on non-verifiable tasks like write a proof of something um these are
not verifiable and then so they use their own model as a judge for whether
or not they got the answer correct. um they have non-reasoning data like sort
of you know write a nice essay um and they use the same SFT data set as what
they used for uh Deepseek V3 and then finally for RLHF they actually still use
GRPO for RLHF which is kind of cool they use the same RL algorithm for everything
um and then they um basically just follow the V3 RLHF pipeline like there's
not really anything different for this post-training part right um how well does it work um works very very well I
think Many of you probably experienced this as well, right? Like R1 was in many
ways a shock because it matched the O1 performance, you know, really kind of
across the board on a very simple recipe, right? Like as I describe this,
I don't think any of you found any of it particularly surprising. Um, but the the
uh outcomes kind of speak for themselves. You know, you've got sort of on the English tasks basically, you
know, tied or matching uh 01 on across the board. really slightly worse on code
models but very very close really across all these different um tasks. The final
thing that uh the R1 paper showed is that you can take these big big models
and you can distill them into other models. So you can take your big deepsee
R1 and you can take those chains of thought like in their case they take
almost a million chains of thought and then they fine-tune Quen with those chains of thought and they actually get
big boosts in sort of math performance relative to the base model which is only
getting something like 50% uh performance on on Amy for for the 32B model. So they get 25 plus% boost on
this task which is which is pretty surprising.
Cool. And then uh finally um there's two I think interesting and good observations from R1 and I think
scientifically maybe this was the the biggest contribution of R1 in a way. So
I think R1 maybe had three contributions scientifically, right? One of it was it
showed that outcome based rewards with GRPO works, right? It's like the positive proof and then R1 also had two
other kind of like negative results kind of uh contributions and they are sort of
contained in the very last part of the R1 report and they basically say okay
like we tried two things uh like pretty extensively. We tried PRM and we also
tried MCTS. Um, and neither of those really helped us at all on like
replicating something like 01, right? And so to to get into a little bit of
detail, right, PRM are basically uh process reward models. Those are kind of like uh systems that can give you
intermediate rewards on a proof, right? So when your model is giving a chain of
thought, a PRM would be able to say, "Oh, you went wrong at this step in the
middle, right?" And obviously that is much richer and very powerful form of feedback. an RL algorithm can make
really really good use of a PRM. But unfortunately, it's also very difficult to get a PRM in the first place. And so,
you know, R1 um and the Deepseek math people like they had gone down this road
of doing uh PRM for a while and they kind of concluded this doesn't work
quite as well as outcome based rewards. And thus far, I think outcomebased rewards remain the way that in which you
would build these models. The second thing that I think hasn't uh really panned out is searchbased methods. I
think lots of people were interested in search based approaches to reasoning. Thus far at least it hasn't really
panned out in the same way that RL and outcome based rewards um has that that
remains I think kind of the strongest uh kind of baseline and system um in this
this universe. Okay. So any questions about um R1 like kind of their setup or
any of the other findings? Yes. PRM GRPO and PRM are kind of two
different Oh yes. Oh yeah. Yeah. That's right. Yes. Okay. Good. Sorry. I said I was
going to mention it, but I didn't. So that is totally on me. That's right.
Exactly. Um and so I think especially for the the PRM, I think it's really
interesting and telling that in DeepSeek math, you know, they were very much convinced by sort of the strength of the
PRM, which is this blue line with PS. And then in R1, they, you know,
concluded that actually this approach that had worked for Deepseek math was not really going to work for R1. and
they had gone with outcome based uh rewards. Yeah, thank you for reminding me. Um I was about to to forget my
promise there. Uh yes consistency is that for I guess ease of
understanding or is do they actually know how it protects performance? Yeah. So so um yeah in this note here they
basically say um if you ablate away the language uh consistency experiment it results in degradation of the model's
performance. Um, but they're gonna put it in anyway because they prefer to have
coots that are more readable to humans. Um, it's an interesting trade-off. Um, there have been lots of research about
whether coots are faithful and they're not truly faithful. We kind of know that. Um, but maybe it's better to have
a slightly more faithful coot than to have the extra, I don't know, half
percentage point performance on Amy. Uh, yes. translated out the end, but if you if
what you care about is that someone can read it, like so uh I mean I'm sure they can do like
translations or or other kinds of like post-processing to make the coots better. And in some ways you might think
of uh OpenAI and and these other vendors efforts to like summarize the coots as
being very similar, right? Like because the raw coots are probably much messier and then they probably like sort of
rationalize it away. Um that is one way and I think that is an effective way to
to get interpretability. Um but I do think if you're interested in somehow if
you aesthetically believe that the raw coot is very important for monitoring and and you know closer interpretability
then I do think you do want something like this. Right. Cool. Okay. Um so now we're going to
move on to uh Kimmy K1.5. Um and why do we study this one? Um, if you look at
the timestamps for when R1 and K1.5 were released, it's it's kind of, you know,
contemporaneous. Um, and it achieves very similar results. It does so using outcome based rewards in RL. It doesn't
use the same algorithm. It has kind of different details and different interesting insights. And so we can
learn about kind of what's the same, what's different, and maybe, you know, what parts are maybe important in this
process. Um so to you know just show you the headline result before we start just
to to get you to to believe that this is a paper that's you know worth being
discussed here right um Kim K 1.5 is the dark blue bars here um you can see
openai's 01 as the the next highest bar so they're you know beating or matching
01 across the board on a bunch of important tasks and they do basically uh
things similar to R1. So they do SFT, they do RL, they have a different RL
algorithm, but they do RL. Um they also describe their data set construction in
a little bit more detail. And this actually gets used in in Quinn 3 later,
so it's worth uh discussing. So let me talk through data. Um as Percy said
earlier, maybe data is the most important thing in your whole pipeline. And so we should always pay attention
when people talk about their kind of data curation, you know, strategies in like a large scale training paper. Um
and so Kimmy 1.5 does several things to try to curate their data set. So what
they first do is they try to balance across different domains like they have
an automated I'm guessing um LM based tagging system to categorize um basically math questions by different
domains and disciplines and then they kind of balance across these to try to
get diversity across different domains. um they exclude even though these are verifiable multiple choice and true
false questions because they argue that these are too easy to to hack or to
randomly guess. So they're only looking for verifiable answers that are kind of short and can be evaluated by things
like regex um or or LM. Um and this is maybe the most interesting piece of the
curation here. Um what they do is they take the model uh that doesn't do any
reasoning uh you know their SFT model um and they have this model generate uh 10
answers um and the pass rate is used um in order to determine whether to include
that example uh or not. Um and I I think the the exact thing they use for their
latest selection strategy is they only select examples that fail best of eight. So if it if if they can get any one out
of a correct, then it's excluded for being too easy. Um SFT data similar to
to R1, very little description. Who knows where they got that from? Um they
just say they do some prompt engineering. So clearly it was distilled from something else. Uh but we don't
really know what they distilled off of. Um so I'll talk about the RL algorithm.
The Kimmy one's kind of interesting. Um it's a different variation. It's actually maybe closer to DPO in a way.
um but you end up with a you know algorithm that I think you'll very much
recognize. So you can kind of think of this in a very interesting way as
convergent evolution of of RL algorithms. So you start once again at the very top. This is our you know
classic goal. You know we're sampling from a data set. We're sampling from our
policy. We want to maximize rewards. We don't want to be too far from our base
policy. So this is the KL regularizer. Um you know if you remember our DPO
derivation you make a nonparametric assumption you say pi star is the optimal policy is an arbitrary function
that means that the reward can be written as you know the log normalizer
plus the ratio of policies right this is the exact same thing we did in dpo and
now you know in dpo what we did was we took these rewards and we plugged them
into the kind of the Bradley Terry preference function we don't have this here right we we're not doing pair wise
preferences so we don't actually take that step. Instead, we write down this equation and we say we know that for the
optimal policy, we're going to have equality here. And so, all we're going to do is we're going to make this a
difference and we're going to add a squared loss on top, right? We're going
to try to drive the left and the right sides close by just adding a squared
loss. It's a reasonable thing to do. People have done things like this before. Um, and this gives us our loss.
It's basically trying to drive uh the right side and the left side of
something that should be an equality for the optimal policy close together. And well, this is a little bit of an exotic
looking object or maybe exotic looking initially, but if you take the gradient, it just looks a lot like gRPO. Uh you
know, you've got your gradients of your policy, right? This is your policy gradient stuff. Um and you've got a
baseline reward. And actually, what's the baseline reward? I'm just going to average um the R within my batch, right?
Um so here this is actually doing something different. This is the normalizing constant um I think over the
batch. Um but you know we're doing essentially similar kinds of baselining as GRPO and we've got a slightly
different like square of the the log loss regularization to keep my policy close rather than doing clipping. Right?
So zooming out, what what's happening here? Very similar to GRPO in that this
first part is a baseline loss, but there's no standard deviation thing happening. This second part is analogous
to the clipping that happens in GRPO, but instead of doing clipping, we're explicitly regularizing the policy,
right? So we've got the same ingredients just in slightly different form. Um, and
so hopefully you can see, you know, that as long as you kind of have this policy
gradient thing and the right baselining and something that looks like regularization, you can get a working RL
algorithm. The other thing that the Kimmy folks do, and in some ways I think this is um more
forward-looking or or they got this more right than the R1 folks, which is that
they realize that, you know, if you're shipping a reasoning model, what you really care about is inference cost. And
if you care about inference cost, you had better try to control the length of
your uh coots, right? If you have really long thinking chains, that's going to
cost you a ton of money or cost your users a ton of money. And so instead of
celebrating the really long coots, the Kimmy folks say, uh, we want to really
compress the coots as much as possible while keeping performance high. Um, and so they have this length reward thing
here. Um, where what they're doing is for kind of each batch, um, they're
looking at the maximum and the minimum lengths. And what you have is lambda
where lambda is roughly like, you know, where are you in the range of lengths
within your batch, right? So if you're at plus.5 um you know you're really short and
negative.5 uh you are really long right um and the reward is basically going to
be lambda whenever you get the answer to be correct. So if your answer is correct
you're going to incentivize yourself to be really short at the very shortest end
of this range. Whereas if your answers are incorrect, you're in this bottom part of this length reward, which means
that you're incentivizing the uh coot lengths to be roughly shorter than the center of the range of the rollouts.
This is a somewhat funky loss to me to be honest, but you can kind of
understand the dynamics of this loss, which is you're incentivizing um sort of correct answers to be as short as
possible and incorrect answers are incentivized to be kind of averageish, right? Um, and so you don't have as
strong of an optimization pressure to to push down incorrect answers uh to be
short. And one final note on this length stuff is the Kimmy folks realize that if
you add this re uh reward early on in training, it stalls RL because, you
know, it basically forces the model to say I'm in a local minimum. I don't get
any of my answers correct. The best I can do is to have my coots really short
and then you just can't get out of that sort of local minimum. And so they
actually only turn this on later on uh during training. So they kind of
initially do a bit of unconstrained RL and then they add this length reward in
um afterwards. Um and they also have additional cool details. Who knows how much of this
stuff is necessary or important, but they actually have a whole curriculum set up. They basically have assigned
difficulty labels. So the data set uh just kind of like top down like they
just manually uh or via LMS kind of annotate uh the difficulty labels. Um,
and then they go from easy to hard in that order. And then they also as
they're uh going on sample problems proportional to one minus success rate. So if you're 100% succeeding, you just
never sample that question uh ever again. Um, and for the rewards, they basically um for code they take problems
with ground truth solutions and they generate a bunch of test cases. Um and
for math they uh basically use actually a reward model um where that's used to
compare like ground truth human written answers to the LM output. So instead of
using something like a reg x or using um simply which is what other people have
done the Kimmy folks actually use a model to do equivalence checking. It's kind of surprising to do this in a
verifiable reward case but you know they don't seem to have a problem. the reward
models are very very accurate um because it's really all it's doing is advanced
string matching. Um one of the things uh that's really cool about the Kimmy paper um is that
they also talk about kind of the infra issues that arise uh doing RL I think I
don't think I've seen any of the other um RL reasoning papers actually talk
about systems almost at all. So, it's nice to see that they're kind of talking
about this, what their structure is, what their their uh layout of this is.
Um, you'll have to deal with this in A5, like I think a very mini version of this
as you implement um things like rollouts in RL. But one thing I'll note, right,
is you know, why is RL so hard to make efficient? And in many ways, it's harder
than normal pre-training to to have your GPUs like fully utilized during RL. Um,
and the reason I think is because there's rollouts involved, right? So you have to be generating sequences and
whenever you're generating sequences not only are you kind of you know slow in
the sense of inference is slow but also you have this other issue which is that
um you have to switch from RL to inference and back and you have to be
passing sort of data back to the RL worker and the RL worker has to pass
model weights to the inference server and vice versa. So you've got all this
sort of message passing um that can happen. And finally um this is unique to
long coot models, but if you have really long coots, batches can become very very
uneven. So you have to to handle that cleverly um somehow. And so um the Kimmy
folks do this, you know, relatively nice but fairly standard thing of having different workers that are assigned to
do the RL updates, having different workers assigned to do inference. Um and they have basically kind of message
passing to be able to pass the weights to the inference worker and the
inference worker can basically make data sets for the RL worker. Um and you know
they have almost the same kinds of setups that you will have. Um they use
VLM for inference. Um and they also do very you know advanced stuff where they
have to have VLM with dummy weights and they have to kill it because of the the
complexities of doing kind of this passing of weights from one worker um to
another. Um, finally, I think one thing that I think is is interesting um that the
Kimmy people show in in their results is they they have like per iteration
results where they show like as RL proceeds like how does you know performance scale and they show really
nice scaling which is in the blue and they also show the growth of the length
of the responses and much like in Dr. GRPO because I don't think their their
RL algorithm is inherently sort of balanced or sorry biased towards longer responses. Most of the um uh sort of
responses actually sort of plateau out at a sort of target length like we saw
with Dr. GRPO rather than grow unboundedly like we did with uh the vanilla grpo.
Cool. Um any questions on on Kimmy before we finally conclude with uh Quen
3? So back to like the RL setup in detail
of Kimmy. Um yeah I was wondering like so I guess like when you're like doing
the robots during like training like the robots the inference is done by the app
right? Yes. And as I update the parameter that will mean that like you
know as they update the model they also need to sync that to the um to the VM
inference through worker and that's what this is for. Yeah. So I think you know
the most annoying part at least with current um libraries of this process is
essentially that step of taking RL weights and putting it into VL1. Uh there is an experimental API that is
supposed to allow you to use uh NCCL collective calls to uh shove a set of
weights into VLM. Um but at least we were thinking about having you use that
for the assignment actually. Uh but it has too many undocumented parameters for it to be a little bit mature. Um and so
maybe next year's iteration this will actually be you know fairly mature technology. But right now I think a lot
of people do things like start a VLM with dummy weights. The weights then get
loaded somehow into memory with sort of hacks on top of VL1. And each iteration they often tear down
VLM to make sure they can free the GPU memory fully. Yeah, there there's a lot of like I
think you know the RL for LMS I think is fairly new still. So I think the
infrastructural support remains a little bit immature but I think in maybe a year
things will actually just get much nicer. Yeah, question back there. You have a lot of like accuracy rewards and
like rewards rewards. How are you supposed to combine them together? Yeah. Um so you how do you combine the
different rewards? Um I think this is one of the RL not quite black magic but
really you know like RL magic things of like you just tune weights like in all
cases um all the rewards are just added together but with weights and how are
the weights determined empirically in order to maximize the downstream performance right um especially for
things like format rewards you can almost think of them as like shaping or
like surrogate rewards like you don't necessarily really care about the formatting reward it's more of a means
to an end to get a good long coot within the tags that will get you the answer
Cool. Okay, so the final uh one I want to talk about is Quen 3. And thankfully uh Quen
3 released their report before the end of the class, so I get to include it.
Um, and you know, I think this is the most recent and modern of the um, RL uh,
for reasoning kind of models to have come out. And so we can kind of see how
they've like built upon the previous works like where they've changed things. Um, and they have actually pretty
interesting scaling and data results that are are are new and unique. Um, so the overall picture is very
similar to what um, R1 and Kimmy have done, right? So Quinn basically take
their base models. um they'll do a long coot sft stage. So that's this first
stage over here. They'll do their reasoning RL. Um they'll do something funky that I'll I'll talk about later
called thinking mode fusion. Um and then they'll do um RLHF RL and then that's
the model that they ship. Of course they then distill that in various ways,
but we can kind of forget about that um for the moment, right? Um so we've
already seen this in R1, right? RLHF comes after reasoning um and then distillation comes yet after uh that.
And we already know a lot of the playbook. So I can actually go through
this fairly fast. Um much like Kimmy, they basically curate the data by filtering for difficulty using best of
end. So if your base model that hasn't been RL can already answer it, if you
sample like end times, then you can just get rid of it, right? Um you they also
do some like decontamination things where they remove things that are too similar to validation data. Um and then
they also manually filter um essentially their SFT set. So like for their initial
SFT data uh for long coots they like manually filter it for whether they are
guessing or whether they actually got it right. Um the one thing that empirically
I think is really interesting about the Quen 3 uh RL results is that they are
actually doing this RL only on 3,995 examples um you know which is a very
small number of examples to be doing this on um and they get pretty good
gains out of the RL process. And so you can view this as you know um RL on
verified rewards as being very efficient. You could also think of this as being um analogous to many sample
efficiency results in the past like people have shown that you can uh instruction tune a model with very few
samples or that you can distill a long coot with very few samples but that
doesn't necessarily mean that it doesn't continue to scale right we don't really know why. What this does show is that
even with very few examples, you can sometimes do RL which is surprising and
cool. Um so what is the two new uh sort of quen specific stuff that they do? um
the the thing that they do is uh this thing called thinking mode fusion which
I think is kind of interesting and where I think the the field or the the various
trends are going is in controlling inference right so what they do is they
want to have both a thinking model and a non-thinking model in the same you know
single set of parameters so what do they do well you know after they train a
model with RL um they have a model that can do thinking and now they're going to
fine-tune it again to do one of two things they're going to fine-tune the
model with some data that has a think tag and then it's going to do the normal
coot thing and you can get this data from yourself right like the original
thinking model can generate this um or you can have a no think tag in which
case it should immediately kind of emit an answer um and you know in this case
they they're going to have to sort of supervise fine-tune the model to know
what no think means and to immediately try to emit um the answer um and one
kind of interesting um side effect of this is that they found that if they do
this training where they train the model to to have a think and a no think tag.
Then what they can do is they can sort of if the model continues to think and
you want to terminate the thinking process, you can kind of actually like terminate the thinking process, add a
special string that's like considering the limited time of the user, I have to
give a solution by thinking directly now and then end think tag and then it sort
of accurately gives the answer. So this gives them a control knob by which they
can sort of more precisely control a maximum number of thinking tokens. Um
and this gives them pretty clean test time scaling from a single model. And so
they can set like a maximum thinking budget. Um and of course the sort of you
know very very maximum out to infinity is just the the original thinking model
but they can kind of early terminate to the left and they can get graceful
degradations uh in model performance. That's you know not too bad at the very
sort of beginning. You can like have the thinking tokens and still get some
pretty good uh performance. And so you know you can look at um Quen
3 also does a nice ablation where they give you the performance at the
reasoning RL stage at the thinking mode fusion stage and at the general RL
stage. Um and one thing that's very interesting to me here is that if you
look at the first two sets of rows the general task and the instruction
following ones um reasoning RL helps thinking mode fusion helps and of course RLHF continues to help here as well
right like kind of everything helps um in this regime but if you look at kind
of math or stem performance you know in the thinking case general RL hurts
performance and in the non-thinking case it helps performance so there really is seems to be at least somewhat of a
trade-off in, you know, do I optimize for general purpose instruction following up here or do I optimize for
like math encoding kind of down here, right? Um, and so those are kind of
interesting sort of properties that are emerging and it'll be cool to see sort
of uh more future models kind of sidestep these uh tradeoffs um somehow.
Okay, cool. So to put that all together um our our sort of initial motivation
was to say RL is very powerful. We kind of figured out that we can do RL with
language models in the RLHF domain. But you can't just like hill climb on noisy
pair wise preferences forever, right? Um so one solution is to pick domains in
which you can't do reward hacking and then just you know go for it, right? RL
and narrow domains is one good solution. Um and GRPO is one very simple algorithm
and hopefully you all kind of have a sense of like okay I can just do policy
gradients with some good baselines and that will enable uh RL on all of these
kinds of verifiable reward domains. Um and then finally um there's lots of successful recipes in the wild and you
hopefully now you've seen you know what's in common, what's different, what implementation tricks uh matter.
Cool. Thanks a lot. Um and I will see you all next week.